到目前为止生命的故事里
我们见到了动物们采取他们的第一步...
..成长...
..寻找一个家...
..并且获得力量...
现在 他们需要一个伴侣
Now, they need a mate.
为了赢得伙伴而竞争
Competition to win a partner
在自然界里是如此的激烈
is so intense in nature,
它创造了最不同寻常的美丽
it has created
both the most extraordinary beauty
和威胁生命的暴力
and life-threatening violence.
一只雄性信天翁
A male waved albatross
在他超过二十年的一生里都只
will have the same partner
for his lifetime
将拥有一个伴侣
of over 20 years.
在独自沿着太平洋觅食后
After feeding alone
over the Pacific Ocean,
这只雄性回到了加拉帕戈斯群岛
this male has returned here
to the Galapagos,
正如同他每年所做的那样
as he does every year,
来等待他的配偶过来找他
to wait for his mate
to come back to him.
其他的已经在重新确立加深羁绊
Others are already
reaffirming their bonds.
随着年份的流逝他们变得越来越老
As the years go by
and they get older,
他们其中之一没法回来的可能性总是存在的
there is always the possibility that
one of them will not make it back.
但是他与他的伴侣的联系是如此的紧固
But his bond with his partner
is so strong,
他将只会坐着等待她
he will simply sit and wait for her.
在自然界里  要想形成这样终身的承诺是很稀少的
In nature, it's rare to form
such a lifelong commitment.
对于大多数动物而言
交配的游戏既单纯又充满暴力竞争性的
For most animals, the mating game is
both brief and fiercely competitive.
一只雌性绿蠵龟
A female green turtle
必须在开放海域里冒着危险生活三十年
must survive the dangers
of the open ocean for 30 years
在她变得足以成熟得以交配之前
before she's mature enough to mate.
她来到了这里  马来西亚浅水滩岸边  来进行繁殖
She's come here, to the shallow
waters off Malaysia, to breed.
一只雄性
A male.
他等待这个机会有好几周了
He's been waiting weeks
for this opportunity.
求偶仪式从最简单的绕圈开始
Courtship begins
with the gentlest of circling...
直到她接受他更进一步之前
..before she accepts his advances.
他们首次一同呼吸
Their first breath together
是交配开始的头几个小时
is the beginning
of several hours of mating.
他将尽他所能的坚持住
He will hold on as tight as he can
来保持使她全身心投入到他一人身上
to keep her all to himself.
不幸地  他们有伙伴
Unfortunately, they have company.
另外一只雄性
Another male.
他将尽一切所能来拆散这对情侣
He will do anything he can
to separate the pair
并且自己和雌性进行交配
and mate with the female himself.
他瞄准了柔软脆弱的部位
He targets
the soft, vulnerable parts.
他把他对手的空气敲了出来
He knocks the air out of his rival.
雌性现在正在为她背上额外的重量而挣扎着
The female is struggling now
with the extra weight on her back,
不久她将需要浮出水面来吸一口气
and soon she will need to surface
to take a breath.
另一只雄性
Another male.
更多竞争
MORE competition.
又来了一只
And here's another.
现在这只雌性在他背上有两只雄性
Now, the female has two males
locked on her back
对于她而言要想上浮到水面上难度倍增
and it's twice as hard for her
to get to the surface.
经过了一小时的争斗后
After an hour of battling,
这对情侣已经被骚扰了七英里
the pair are being harassed
by seven males.
但是雄性们是如此的兴奋
他们开始攻击彼此
But the males are so excited,
they start attacking each other.
在骚乱中  这对情侣脱离了表面
In the commotion, the couple
break away for the surface.
这对情侣做出了逃脱
The pair manage to make their escape...
留下处于混乱困惑状态中的雄性对手们
..leaving the rival males
milling around in confusion.
最终  他们可以和平的进行交配了
Finally, they can mate in peace.
在这场交配的游戏当中  通常是雄性
In the mating game, it's usually
the males who take the risks
承担起风险并且付出最多的那方
他叫
新几内亚火焰别墅鸟不通过打架的方式赢取伴侣
它的战略是奉献上一场表演
His strategy is to put on a show.
他首先撘筑个舞台
First, he builds a stage.
在繁殖的季节里 他花费一个星期建造这个建筑
In the breeding season, he spends
a week creating this construction,
叫做凉亭    在巴布亚新几内亚的森林里
called a bower,
in the forests of Papua New Guinea.
他痴迷于细节
He's a stickler for detail.
舞台准备好了
The stage is set.
是用泥巴粉刷的时间了
Time to paint it with mud.
这形成了一个较暗的背景
That makes a darker background,
这将对比凸显其明亮的色彩
which will set off
his magnificent colours.
接下来  关于服装的方面有着不同的选择
Next, there are difficult
decisions about the set-dressing.
或许有点太无趣了
Perhaps a bit dull.
仍有进步的余地
There's still room for improvement.
完美
Perfect.
是时候叫上观众了
Time to call in the audience...
他鸣叫着
HE SQUAWKS
如果有任何人感兴趣的话
..if anyone's interested.
这可能需要花费一些时间
This could take some time.
吸引注意力是吸引伴侣重要关键的部分
Attracting attention is
an essential part of winning a mate.
世界的海洋被明亮的颜色所覆盖
The world's oceans
are filled with brilliant colours,
所有都是被设计使得外表更加显眼
all designed
to make their wearers conspicuous.
不幸的是，这只小的，日本河豚是平淡的
Unfortunately this small,
Japanese puffer fish is dull,
几乎就看不见
almost to the point of invisibility,
但为了补偿
but to compensate,
他或许是大自然界里最伟大的艺术家
he is probably nature's
greatest artist.
为了获取雌性的注意力
To grab a female's attention,
它创造了一些令人难以置信的东西
he creates something that almost
defies belief.
他唯一的工具是他的鳍
His only tools are his fins.
在他的脑海里
一个完美的数学计划
In his head,
a plan of mathematical perfection.
他挖开沙子  把它们分开成细小的粒子
He ploughs the sand, breaking it up
into the finest of particles.
这些不仅仅是要拿来当做垃圾扔掉的贝壳
These shells aren't just
rubbish to be removed.
他用他来搭建他建筑物的桥梁
He uses them to decorate
the bridges of his construction.
他一刻都不能停息
He can't rest for more
than a moment,
必须连续不断的工作上一周每天二十四小时
but must work 24 hours a day
for a week,
否则水流将会毁掉他的建筑
or the current
will destroy his creation.
一个最后的清理 然后他的建筑物大功告成
A final tidy-up
and his masterpiece is complete.
自然界里没有任何一种其他动物
Nowhere else in nature
does an animal construct something
建一个像他一样又复杂又如此完美的东西
as complex and perfect as this.
如果这都不能让他获得瞩目  没东西会了
If this doesn't get him noticed,
nothing will.
现在他准备好要接受视察了
Now it's ready for inspection.
一只雌性  膨胀搭载着满满的卵
A female, swollen with eggs.
为了保证她能够获得最佳的视野
他鼓励她进入中心区域内
To make sure she gets the best view,
he encourages her into the centre.
审查完毕 她退了出去
Inspection over, she withdraws
等待着最后阶段的过程
to await the final stage
of the process.
到了下一个清晨  所有最柔软的沙子现在都到了中间
By the next morning, all the softest
sand is now in the middle.
展示场的中间现在被弄平了
The centre of the arena
has been flattened.
就在这个点  她来了
Right on cue, here she is.
这正是她想要的
This is what she wanted.
对于她的卵而言  这是个理想的床
It's a perfect bed for her eggs.
雄性抓住了她的脸颊  并且开始对她微小的卵进行受精
The male now grasps her cheek and
then fertilises her minuscule eggs.
快速轻弹他的鳍   他将卵埋了起来
And with a quick flick of his fins,
he buries them.
他们继续着如此进行直到她完成生蛋的过程
They carry on like this
until she has finished laying.
他一个小时毫不修饰的感情在她的脸颊上留下了一个爱的咬痕
An hour of his rough affection
leaves a love bite on her cheek.
最终，她离开
Finally, she leaves.
他留下来翻转这些卵直到他们孵化
He stays to fan the eggs
until they hatch,
直到他出众的艺术品从他周围旁边消散
while his extraordinary work of art
fades away around him.
南极的南乔治亚
South Georgia in the Antarctic.
一只雄性海狗
A male fur seal.
他大约处于风华正茂的十岁年华
He's about ten years old
and in his prime.
他即将上岸面对他一生中的战斗
He's coming ashore to face
the fight of his life.
他甚至可能死在海滩上
He may even die on this beach.
首次  它强大到足以赢取一块
For the first time,
he is strong enough to try to win
能够吸引一群雌性的领土
a territory that could attract
a harem of females.
但与他们拥有着同样想法的对手还有很多
But there are plenty of rivals here
with the same idea.
这些只是前面几轮
These are only
the preliminary rounds.
真正的战斗会在雌性到来后展开
The real struggle will begin
once the females arrive.
仅仅几个星期后  海滩上挤满了
Just a week later,
females have filled the beach
正在为她们幼崽的诞生选择着最好领土的雌性
choosing the best territories in
which to give birth to their pups.
这只雄性现在有一群雌性
This male now has a harem
of a dozen females
他现在必须防御他们
and he's going to have
to defend them.
他嫉妒的邻居们将会准备利用任何虚弱的迹象
His jealous neighbours will be ready
to exploit any sign of weakness.
只有雌性完成了交配
It's only once the females
have given birth
雄性才能与之交配
that males can mate with them.
现在这只雄性现在必须确保他一个人养育着下一年的后代
Now this male must ensure that he
alone fathers next year's offspring.
但这同时也是对手的机会
But this is the rival's chance too.
他必须动作快
He must act fast.
她将不会发现他们全像这只一样这么好威胁
He won't find them all
as easy as this to intimidate.
新的雄性们从海洋里上岸
New males pound up from the sea,
意图着测试领土所有者
intent on testing
the territory holders.
随着在他的后面有越来越多等待中的人
With many more waiting behind them.
最大的战斗尚未到来呢
The biggest battles are yet to come.
在交配游戏中  通常不是雄性
Usually in the mating game,
it's not the males
而是雌性做主
but the females who call the shots.
但这只雄性长尾侏儒鸟正尝试着
And this male long-tailed manakin
is trying to win over
赢取世界上最挑剔之一的雌性的芳心
one of the world's
choosiest females.
他在这里  哥斯达黎加练习着他的动作
He's been practising his moves
here in Costa Rica
长达数十年
for as long as a decade.
这里有另外一只雄性
There's another male here too.
这只新来的不是对手
而是一个年轻的伙伴
Only the newcomer is not a rival,
he is a junior partner.
他们彼此知己知彼
他们可以承接完成彼此的呼唤
They know each other so well,
they can finish each other's calls.
但这并不是他们同步了的意思
But that's not all that
they have synchronised.
他们是师傅和学徒
They are master and apprentice.
学徒为这个练习了好几年了
The apprentice has also been
practising for many years.
但现在他必须模仿老师的每一个动作
But now he must copy
the master's every move.
实际上
老师也需要他的同僚
In fact,
the master needs his wingman
正是由于雌性甚至不会正眼瞧一个独奏者
as a female won't even
look at a solo performer,
更重要的是   他希望看到完美无间的配合
and what's more,
she will expect perfect harmony,
因此他们每天一起练习
so they practice together every day.
最终他们准备好了
At last they're ready.
她来了
Here she is.
排演完毕
Rehearsal over,
他们的表演是超过十年辛勤工作的结果
their performance is the result
of more than ten years' hard work.
她不能忍受出错
She won't tolerate a single slip-up.
突然间大师跳舞的时间到了
Suddenly the master
calls time on the dance...
学徒被驱赶走了
..and the apprentice is banished.
只有大师能得以交配
Only the master gets to mate.
对于这个学徒  在他的老师死掉之前
For the apprentice, there will be
no reward until his master dies
他都将没有回报  然后才得以取而代之
and he can take his place.
交配有时可以是一场很长的游戏
The mating game can sometimes be
a long game.
一只来自澳大利亚的雄性孔雀跳蛛
A male peacock jumping spider
from Australia
寻找着伴侣
on a quest for a mate.
当你的体型只有一颗米粒大小的时候
And when you're the size
of a grain of rice,
几乎这里的任何东西都会变得很危险
almost anything here
could be dangerous.
他正在寻找着任何雌蜘蛛朝着这里前进的迹象
He's searching for any sign that
a female spider came this way.
而他发现了什么
And he's found something.
带着雌性味道的蜘蛛丝
Spider silk,
with the scent of a female.
他所需要的只是跟着他
He just needs to follow it...
无论这将引领他至何处
..wherever it leads him.
其他的雄性展开了相同的追求并引起了很可怕的结果
Other males have gone on the same
quest and have come to a grisly end.
这就是那只雌性而且他看起来并不十分处于交配状态
Here's the female
and she doesn't look very amorous.
事实上 他把任何一只达不到她要求
In fact, she kills every male
的雄性都给杀了
who doesn't match up
to her expectations.
为了赢取她的芳心他能做些什么呢
What can he do to win her over?
跳舞
Dance.
为他的生命而跳舞
Dance for his life.
他将需要一种停止表演的把戏来避免成为盘中餐
He will need a show-stopping trick
to avoid becoming lunch.
他的扇子展了开来
With his fan unfurled,
他开始了一系列更加复杂的舞蹈动作
he begins an ever more complicated
series of dance moves
尝试着勾引他
to try and seduce her.
最终她屈服于他的推进并且允许和她进行交配
At last she succumbs to his advances
and allows him to mate with her.
他达到了她的预期
He matched her expectations.
但她仍然杀死了他
But she kills him anyway.
最终  他的尸体将成为
After all, his body will make
the perfect meal
养育她的卵的完美的午餐
with which to nourish their eggs.
回到巴布亚新几内亚Back in Papua New Guinea,
这只雄性火焰园丁鸟仍在在为吸引异性尽力做着尝试
the male flame bowerbird is still
doing his best to attract a female.
最终他得到了回复
And at last he gets a response.
不幸的是  这是个年轻的男性
Unfortunately, it's a young male.
更糟的是   他带了个朋友
And worse, he's brought a friend.
他们正在无拘无束地用他的巢进行着练习
They're taking liberties,
practising on his bower.
他看起来不知如何是好
He doesn't seem to know
what to do about it.
但是  够就是够了
But enough is enough.
骚动引起了另外一只成年雄性的注意
The commotion attracts the attention
of another adult male,
一个邻居和对手
a neighbour and rival.
摧毁掉了他的凉亭
他甚至把他的装饰品给偷走了
Having destroyed the bower,
he even steals the decorations.
凉亭的主人回头只发现一片废墟的景象
The owner arrives back
to find a scene of destruction.
没有一只雌性将朝这种废墟看第二眼
No female's going to look twice
at this mess.
他必须重头再做一遍
He'll just have to start
all over again.
在生命里   在求偶的过程里总会有对手
In life, there will always be rivals
in the mating game.
日本森林的秋天
Autumn in the forests of Japan.
日本猕猴的交配季节
The mating season
for Japanese macaques.
猴群的领导者现在应经超过了二十岁
This dominant male
is over 20 years old.
年龄使得他的视力变得模糊
Age has clouded one eye.
多年来他有着一群雌性
He has had a harem of females
for many years.
他可以随心所欲与她们交配
And he can mate with them unopposed.
但岁月不饶人
But time catches up with everyone.
年轻的雄性竞争者们都在领土范围外面溜达着
Young rival males are hanging out
on the perimeter,
监视着她的雌性们
eyeing up his females.
多年以来   年长的蓝眼猕猴一直是这棵树的权威
For years, Old Blue-eye has asserted
his authority from this tree.
但他的权威正逐渐消逝
But his authority is waning
此刻他被背叛了
and the moment his back is turned,
他的雌性们被年轻的雄性给吸引走了
his females are lured away
by younger males.
在整个森林里  他的雌性正在私底下进行着秘密的事情
Throughout the forest, his females
are conducting secret affairs.
蓝眼  尝试着通过在森里的边缘巡逻来保护她的女性
Blue-eye tries to guard his females
by patrolling the edge of the troop.
抓个现行
Caught in the act.
他攻击了这个不忠诚的女性
He attacks his unfaithful female.
他重新确认了他的统治地位
He has reasserted his authority.
或者他是如此认为的
Or so he thinks.
一旦这只年老的雄性合上眼睛
The moment the old male
shuts his eyes,
他的后宫们又出去浪了
his females are off again.
大部分下一年的幼儿们将由他的对手们抚养
Most of next year's babies
will be fathered by his rivals.
他将永远无从得知
And he will never know.
在巴布亚新几内亚
In Papua New Guinea,
园丁鸟仔细地重建并且重新装饰了他的凉亭
the bowerbird has lovingly rebuilt
and redecorated his bower.
另外一个拜访者
Another visitor.
这次是个雌性
This time it's a female.
这正是他需要她的地方
This is just where he wants her.
是时候开始表演了
Time to begin the show.
首先  他的眼孔缩小放大着
First, he expands
his pupils alternately.
这是一次很迷人的展示
It's an oddly mesmerising display.
一点准备
A spot of limbering up
伴随着一阵奇怪的喘息呼唤
accompanied by a weird
and wheezy call
从他的喉咙深处发出
from deep in his throat.
现在 是时候轮到他精彩的表演了
Now, it's time for his
grand performance.
她摇晃着他的尾巴就像斗牛士的披风
He waves his wing
like a matador's cape.
她看起来似乎惊呆了
She appears to be transfixed.
这是引人注目的
但看起来他似乎必须做得更多
This is certainly eye-catching
but it seems he needs to do more.
很慷慨地   她留给了他个提示
Generously, she drops him a hint.
是有关鸟和花束的关系
It's the bird equivalent
of a bouquet of flowers.
一切进行的很顺利
It's all going so well,
是时候给她的胸部几个头槌了
it's time to get physical
with a few head-butts to her chest.
一次最后的奋斗来为几个星期的努力划上句号
One final flourish
to cap weeks of effort.
但有什么搞错了
But something's wrong.
他的对手回来了
在最糟糕的时刻
His rival is back,
and at the worst possible moment.
他该怎么办
What should he do?
对于这支雌性   已经错过时间了
For the female, the moment has gone.
有时候 无论你做什么  总没有效果
Sometimes, whatever you do,
things just don't work out.
在南乔治亚海滩上的海狗
On the fur seal beach
in South Georgia,
争斗已经持续不间断了两星期
the fighting has been relentless
for two weeks.
血迹斑斑伤痕累累
这只海牛在他的领土上坚守着  还有他的后宫们
Bloodied and scarred,
this bull has held on to his ground
面对着侵略者们
and his harem against allcomers.
但这还没完
But it's not over yet.
对手们不断前来
The rivals keep coming.
这个新来的看起来十分强壮
This new one looks
particularly powerful.
当两只雄性像这样势均力敌的时候
When two bulls are as evenly matched
as this,
它们能够互相捶打攻击长达二十分钟
they can trade blows
for 20 minutes.
地主海牛十分疲乏
The resident bull is tiring.
几个星期的战斗使得他精疲力竭
The weeks of fighting
have taken too great a toll.
突然之间  他的邻居加入了攻击
Suddenly, his neighbours
join in the attack.
被打败  他被赶出了他的领土
Overwhelmed, he's driven
from his territory
和永远离开了这个社区
and out of the colony forever.
繁殖季节几乎要结束了
而海豹们即将离开
The breeding season is almost over
and the seals will soon leave.
这个被遗弃的   这只受到了致命伤的海牛将死在这里
Now an outcast, this mortally
wounded bull will die here...
但他将作为赢家死去
..but he will die a winner.
他掌控领土的时间够长足以繁衍下一代
He held his territory for
long enough to father offspring.
自然界的成功全关乎繁衍下一代
Success in nature is all about
creating the next generation,
无论付出什么代价
whatever it takes.
一只雄性信天翁等待着他的伴侣从开阔的海洋回来
A male waved albatross waits for his
mate to return from the open sea.
这会是她吗
Could this be her?
或是这个
Or this?
有任何她身上熟悉的东西吗
Is there something familiar
about her?
相识
Recognition.
重逢
Reunited.
他们得以回复他们长久的关系
And they can resume
their long-standing relationship.
如果爱情 正如同我们所了解的那样 存在于大自然中
If love, as we understand it,
exists in nature,
这必定就是它了
then surely this must be it.
他们一生的纽带将帮助他们一起
Their lifelong bond will help them
face the final chapter
面对生命故事里的最后篇章
of life's story together,
父母关系
parenthood.
生命的故事团队发现的最意想不到的故事
One of the most unexpected stories
found by the Life Story team
是一只小鱼在沙子里做了一个麦田圈
was that of a small fish who makes
crop circles in the sand.
不幸的是 他是在南日本海的
Unfortunately, it builds them right
at the bottom of a bay
海湾正下方建造它的
in southern Japan.
所以你将要如何拍摄一只在海底十三英尺深的小鱼呢
So how do you film a tiny fish,
13 metres under the sea?
水下专家卡梅隆 Hugh米勒的解决方案是 HughSpecialist underwater cameraman
Hugh Miller's solution
在海床建造一个影视棚
is to build a film studio
on the sea bed.
这是一个方框，一个方框盒
This is a quad, a quad pod.
它有点像三脚架但是他有四条腿
It's a bit like a tripod
but it's got four legs
使得我们能够将摄影机下沉到非常低的海床上
and lets us get the camera
very, very low to the sea bed.
这个金属三角形将会作为浮力光亮船桅
This metal triangle is going to be
the buoyant light rig,
因此他就像在海底的一丝微弱的光线
so it's like a little ray
of sunshine down at the bottom
但这是它首次被投入使用
of the sea, but this is
the first time it's been used
我们将看看它能否行得通
and we're going to find out
if it works or not.
Hugh也设计了一种水下起重机
Hugh has also designed
an underwater crane
来展示整个结构的复杂程度
to reveal the full complexity
of the nest structure.
但无论器具有多好   队伍仍需在一个巨大的海湾中
But however good the equipment,
the team will still have to find
寻找这条十二厘米长的鱼
the 12cm-long fish
in a big bay.
为了这个  他们前往请教专家
For that, they turn to the expert.
七十岁的 绘理 绪方
70-year-old Yogi Okata
首次发现神秘的麦田怪圈
first discovered the mysterious
crop circles
和制造它们的河豚鱼
and the puffer fish that makes them.
他和他的潜水伙伴东洋即将
He and his dive buddy Toyo
are going to search
探索海床方圆数英里的地希望能找到鱼
several square miles of sea bed,
hoping to locate a fish.
找到鱼很困难  伪装得很好
Fish is very difficult,
almost camouflaged very well,
就像沙子一样
因此我只能看到眼睛或者影子
like almost sandy, so just
I can see shadow or just eye.
这将会很困难
So it's very difficult.
但最终东洋和与仪得到了好消息
But eventually Toyo and Yogi
have good news,
他们找到了这个海湾里被证明是唯一的雄性河豚鱼
they've found what turns out to be
the only male fish in the bay.
十二英尺 好的
12 metres, yeah.
他们甚至画了一幅地图来让Hugh找到他
They've even drawn a map for
Hugh to find it.
如果我跟丢了
我就拿着这个
If I get lost,
I'll be holding this.
是时候搭建摄影棚了
Time to build the studio.
所有的器材都被带到了海床上以细心组装
All the kit is taken to the sea bed
to be carefully assembled.
最后的问题是几乎没有阳光
The last thing in place
is Hugh's little ray of sunshine.
鱼在几天内将不会开始筑巢
The fish won't start building
a new nest for several days,
所以仍有时间测试他对器材的反应
so there's time to test
his reaction to the kit
随着他将卵扇到他的老旧的 崩坏的巢穴
while he fans his eggs on his old,
disintegrating nest.
他显然面对摄像机不感到害羞
He's certainly not camera shy.
现在Hugh首次仔细看这条鱼
And now Hugh's had his first good
look at the fish.
最大的惊讶是这条鱼
The biggest surprise was the fish
is a little bit smaller
比我所希望的小了一点
than I first hoped.
事实上他大约只有，好吧，这点大小
In fact he's only, well,
he's really only about this big.
因此突然间面对可能只有我预计
And so to suddenly be faced
with a fish
中一半大小的鱼
that's probably half the size
of what I was hoping,
我认为这可能比我一开始所想的
I thought, well, this is going to be
a little bit harder
还要困难一点
than I first thought.
东洋和与仪保持着注意
Yogi and Toyo keep watch
而且不久他们便发现了这条鱼准备筑一个新巢
and it's not long before they spot
the fish starting to construct
与仪一度认为需要几天才能完工的
a new nest, which Yogi expects will
take him seven days to complete.
他三小时内完成了的事实惊讶了所有的人
He surprises everyone
by finishing it in three.
Yogi示意摄制组明天黎明要为
Yogi warns the crew
to be ready at dawn the next day
雌鱼的拜访做好准备
for a visit from a female fish.
他们花费三小时蹲在相机前
They spend three hours
crouched over the camera
来拍摄正如Yogi预料所展开的那样的行动
to film the action as it unfolds,
just as Yogi predicted.
发生了什么？  产卵
So what happened? Spawning!
逮到你们了！
We've got it.
这个小伙子做得很好了
The little chap was doing
very well for himself.
但这只雄性巢建得太快
But the male built his nest so fast
以至于Hugh没有时间拍摄从上而下的镜头
that Hugh never had time
to film a top-down shot
来揭示他最终辛勤工作的结果
for the ultimate reveal
of his hard work.
这要求摄制团队也成为建筑者
This requires the crew
to become builders too.
他们搭建了‘A’字骨架以
They build an A frame to hold
the camera perfectly steady
在巢穴之上稳固地支撑摄像机
well above the nest.
Yogi和东洋把框架放在老的巢穴附近
Yogi and Toyo position
the frame near to the old nest.
现在队伍只需要等待
Now the crew just have to wait
鱼完成照料他的蛋并且恢复继续建筑
for the fish to finish tending
his eggs and resume building.
但是几天之后
传来了坏消息
But a few days later,
there's bad news.
我们几天以来正收听着来自于南方的台风的新闻
We've been watching a typhoon system
far to the south of us
而到目前为止我们仍未确切感受到它
for a number of days, and we haven't
really felt its effects until now,
今天将会是河豚鱼
and today was going to be
the first day of the puffer fish
进行他下一轮建设的第一个循环
beginning its next cycle
of nest building,
它彻底被毁了
and it's been completely blown.
因此比起继续拍摄
So rather than going in
with the cameras
开始新一轮的循环
and starting the new cycle,
we're actually going in
我们开始修复起器材
这实在是很遗憾
just to recover equipment,
which is a real shame,
因为我们不知道接下来会发生什么
cos we don't know what's going
to happen next, really.
自从风暴过境以来已经经过了五天
It's five days before
the storm blows through.
最终海洋平静了下来  并且视线清晰度得以恢复
Finally, the sea calms down
and the visibility returns.
但对于Yogi和东洋
一切又回到了原点
But for Yogi and Toyo,
it's back to square one.
它们必须重新找一遍鱼
They must find the fish
all over again.
他们一天又一天地找  而东洋
担任着译员的角色，回复报告道：
Day after day they search, and Toyo,
acting as interpreter, reports back.
嗯...没巢穴...没有雄性
Um... No nest, no male.
消息稍微好了一些
The news gets slightly better.
我们找到了一条鱼
We find a fish.
只有一条但是没巢
Just one fish but no nest.
我们在二十米深处发现了他
We find the male
at the 20 metre deeps,
但是没有制作圆圈
but not make circle.
风暴拖延了这只鱼的建筑工作
The storm has put the fish off
his construction work.
时间到了  而队伍不情愿地开始
Time is up and the team reluctantly
start to dismantle
拆分摄影器材
the underwater studio.
但是这条鱼即将带给我们一个惊喜
But the fish has one more surprise
in store.
它发生在不能再更晚的时候  最后一次下潜
Well, it just couldn't come at
a later point, the last dive.
我们正准备收拾器材
We're, we're going in
to pull out the kit,
而那里正有一只正在筑巢的雄性
and there's a male making a nest.
最后一次拍摄最棒镜头的机会
One final chance to get the perfect
top shot from the A frame.
一个展现这条鱼无与伦比艺术感的镜头
A shot that truly does justice to
the fish's extraordinary artistry.
下回生命的故事里
Next time on Life Story,
动物们怀着强大责任心养育着后代
animals raise offspring
with great commitment,
坏习惯
bad behaviour,
需要学的教训
lessons to be learned
生与死的抉择
and life and death choices.
成功意味着为未来留下后代
Success means
leaving a legacy for the future.
未来花园纪录片爱好者字幕组出品
时间仓促  欢迎指错